Wunderlich, Frieda; Papers ger101
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Frieda Wunderlich Papers
1920-1941
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Wunderlich, Frieda, 1884-1965
ger101
1 cubic ft.
Wunderlich taught at the New School for Social Research and was an authority on farm labor in Germany and the Soviet Union. The bulk of the collection consists of publications of Frieda Wunderlich, primarily in the anti-Hitler periodical Soziale Praxis, which she edited from 1923 until she emigrated to the United States in 1933.
Biographical Sketch
Frieda Wunderlich was one of ten German professors brought to the United States by the New School for Social Research in 1933 to form the Graduate Faculty of the New School, also known as the "University in Exile".
Frieda Wunderlich was born in Berlin Germany on November 8, 1884. She received her doctorate in economics from the University of Freiburg in 1919 and became a professor at the Handelshochschule in Berlin shortly after graduation.
Wunderlich became one of the leading women figures in pre-Hitler Germany, holding positions in the Berlin City Council and the Prussian State Parliament. In 1930 she was appointed to Judge of the German Supreme Court for Social Welfare.
During the years from 1923 to 1933, she was the editor of the anti-Hitler publication Soziale Praxis, to which she contributed numerous articles on social welfare, unemployment and labor. In 1926 she published Produktivität, which received a great deal of attention not only in Germany, but in the United States as well.
After leaving Hitler's Germany to come to New York and the New School for Social Research in 1933, Wunderlich remained on the faculty for the next two decades. In 1939, she became the first woman in the United States to be elected as Dean of a graduate school when she was elected Dean of the Graduate Faculty of Political and Social Science of the New School. Dr. Wunderlich wrote a series of books on labor and social problems, eight of which were published in the United States and include: Labor under German Democracy (1940), Arbitration, 1918-1933 (1940), British Labor and the War (1941), German Labor Courts (1946), and Farm Labor in Germany, 1810-1945 (1961).
Chronology of Events:
1884 Born in Berlin, Germany on November 8.
1919 Received a doctorate in economics from the University of Freiburg.
1919-1933 Professor at the Handelshochschule, Berlin.
1923-1933 Editor of Soziale Praxis, an anti-Hitler political weekly.
1925 Became a member of the Berlin City Council and the Prussian Landtag for the Deutsche Demokratische Partei (DDP).
1926 Publication of Produktivität.
1930 Appointed to Judge of the German Supreme Court for Social Welfare. Promoted to Professor at the Berufspädagogisches Institut, Berlin.
1933 Brought over from Germany as an expert in social policy by the New School for Social Research.
1933-1954 Member of the Graduate Faculty of Political and Social Science of the New School for Social Research.
1939 January 4 - Elected Dean of the Graduate Faculty of Political and Social Science, the first woman dean of an American graduate school.
1965 Died on December 9 in East Orange, New Jersey.
Scope and Contents
The Frieda Wunderlich Papers have been divided into five series: 1) Biographical materials, 1927-1931; 2) Correspondence, 1926-1930; 3) Protokolls and transcripts of meetings, 1928-1931; 4) Unpublished writings, speech texts, 1927-1933; and 5) Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich, 1920-1941.
The bulk of the collection consists of publications of Frieda Wunderlich, primarily in the anti-Hitler periodical Soziale Praxis, which she edited from 1923 until she emigrated to the United States in 1933. In addition, there are several typescripts of speeches delivered by Wunderlich in Germany during the years 1927-1933. The collection contains only a few letters (primarily concerned with speeches delivered by Dr. Wunderlich), but does contain numerous clippings documenting Dr. Wunderlich's activities during the years 1927-1931.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized as follows:
.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were transferred to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, from the New School for Social Research in New York in 1979.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Labor; Social work education.; Agricultural laborers -- Germany.; Agricultural laborers -- Soviet Union.; Manuscripts.; Correspondence.; Agriculture; New School for Social Research (New York, N.Y.: 1919-1997)
- Biographical materials, 1927-1931; 1; 7 file folders
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists primarily of newspaper clippings about Dr. Wunderlich's activities, promotions, and lectures delivered during the years 1927 to 1931.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Clippings about Wunderlich, 1927 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 1)
  - Clippings pertaining to the 40. Deutscher Fürsorgetag, 1927 May (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 2)
  - Clippings about Wunderlich, 1928 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 3)
  - Clippings about Wunderlich, 1929 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 4)
  - Clippings about Wunderlich, 1930 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 5)
  - Clippings about Wunderlich, 1931 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 6)
  - Lecture announcements, 1928-1931 (Box 1 (1-Biographical materials), Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1926-1930; 2; 1 file folder
  Primarily correspondence relating to lectures.
  - Correspondence primarily dealing with lectures given by Wunderlich, Undated (Box 1 (2-Correspondence), Folder 8)
  - Simon, Helene, 1929 (Box 1 (2-Correspondence), Folder 8a)
- Protokolls and transcripts of meetings, 1928-1931; 3; 6 file folders
  This series contains transcripts of testimonies of Frieda Wunderlich before sessions of the Landstag and other governmental representative bodies.
  - Protokolls of meetings, 1928-1930 (Box 1 (3-Protokolls and transcripts of meetings), Folder 9)
  - "Amtlicher stenographischer Bericht über die Sitzung der Berliner Stadtverordnetenversammlung am 3. Mai 1928". Printed transcript of Wunderlich's testimony, Undated (Box 1 (3-Protokolls and transcripts of meetings), Folder 10)
  - "Amtlicher stenographischer Bericht über die Sitzung der Berliner Stadtverordnetenversammlung am 17. März 1930". Printed transcript of Wunderlich's testimony, Undated (Box 1 (3-Protokolls and transcripts of meetings), Folder 11)
  - "Außerordentliche Sitzung am 29. April 1930". Printed transcript of Wunderlich's testimony, Undated (Box 1 (3-Protokolls and transcripts of meetings), Folder 12)
  - "Preußischer Landtag 198. Sitzung am 31. Januar 1931". Printed transcript of Wunderlich's testimony, Undated (Box 1 (3-Protokolls and transcripts of meetings), Folder 13)
  - "Preußischer Landtag Sitzung am 26. November 1931". Printed transcript of Wunderlich's testimony, Undated (Box 1 (3-Protokolls and transcripts of meetings), Folder 14)
- Unpublished writings, speech texts, 1927-1933; 4; 9 file folders
  This series contains primarily texts of lectures delivered by Dr. Wunderlich from 1927 to 1933.
  - "Verordnung über die Fürsorgepflicht vom 3. Februar 1924", Undated (Box 1 (4-Unpublished writings, speech texts), Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous speech texts, ca. 1927 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished writings, speech texts), Folder 16)
  - "Der Produktivitätsbegriff", Undated (Box 1 (4-Unpublished writings, speech texts), Folder 17)
  - Speech on "Wirtschaft, Sozialpolitik und Wohlfahrtspflege", ca. 1927 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished writings, speech texts), Folder 18)
  - Speech on German welfare system, 1928 March 20 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished writings, speech texts), Folder 19)
  - Speech on "Sozialpolitik und Wohlfahrtspflege", Undated (Box 1 (4-Unpublished writings, speech texts), Folder 20)
  - Speech on productivity, 1931 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished writings, speech texts), Folder 21)
  - Speech on "Socialpolitik und Arbeitsrecht", 1932 April 21 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished writings, speech texts), Folder 22)
  - "Die deutsche Sozialversicherung", 1932 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished writings, speech texts), Folder 23)
  - "Social Insurance in Germany". German version of "Die deutsche Sozialversicherung", 1932 July 9-1932 July 10 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished writings, speech texts), Folder 24)
  - "Reform der Arbeitslosenversicherung", 1932 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished writings, speech texts), Folder 25)
  - Speech on "Berufsschulen", 1932 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished writings, speech texts), Folder 26)
  - Speech on unemployment insurance, 1932 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished writings, speech texts), Folder 27)
  - Speech on unemployment, 1933 April 7 (Box 1 (4-Unpublished writings, speech texts), Folder 28)
- Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich, 1920-1941; 5; 44 file folders
  This is the largest series in the collection and contains primarily publications by Wunderlich in the periodical Soziale Praxis, which she also edited for over ten years, 1923-1933. Also included in this series are reviews of Wunderlich's writings.
  - "Die gleitende Lohnskala"Deutsche Tiefbau-Zeitung, No. 37, 340-342, 15 September 1920 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 29)
  - "Teuerungszahlen"Deutsche Tiefbau-Zeitung, No. 38, 348-349, 22 September 1920 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 30)
  - "Sozialpolitik und Wirtschaftspolitik. Betrachtungen über den Ort der Sozialpolitik"Soziale Praxis und Archiv für Volkswohlfahrt, No. 31, 707-710, 2 August 1923 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 31)
  - "Aus den deutschen Gewerbeaufsichtsberichten. (Sachsen, Württemberg, Hamburg, Braunschweig), I, II, IV, V, VI"Soziale Praxis und Archiv für Volkswohlfahrt, No. 28, 29, 34, 35, 39, 12 July-27 September 1923 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 32)
  - "Deutschlands 'soziales Dumping'"Soziale Praxis und Archiv für Volkswohlfahrt, No. 9, 161-164, 28 February 1924 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 33)
  - "Der Streit um das 'Soziale Dumping'. Zur Auseinandersetzung über den Abbau der Sozialpolitik"Soziale Praxis und Archiv für Volkswohlfahrt, No. 17, 337-341, 14 April 1924 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 34)
  - "Die Sozialpolitik in der Schweiz"Soziale Praxis und Archiv für Volkswohlfahrt, No. 36, 743-745, 4 September 1924 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 35)
  - "Nelsons Sozialpolitik I, II, III"Soziale Praxis und Archiv für Volkswohlfahrt, No. 48-50, 27 November-11 December 1924 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 36)
  - "Ein Gang durch die deutsche Heimarbeitausstellung 1925"Soziale Praxis und Archiv für Volkswohlfahrt, No. 19-25, 7 May-18 June 1925 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 37)
  - "Die Denkschrift der Vereinigung der deutschen Arbeitgeberverbände zur Lohnfrage"Soziale Praxis und Archiv für Volkswohlfahrt, No. 26, 567-571, 25 June 1925 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 38)
  - "Psychoshysische Arbeitsforschung"Soziale Praxis und Archiv für Volkswohlfahrt, No. 38, 836-839, 17 September 1925 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 39)
  - "Stand und Entwicklungsmöglichkeiten der Fabrikpflege in Deutschland"Soziale Praxis und Archiv für Volkswohlfahrt, No. 49, 1107-1110, 3 December 1925 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 40)
  - "Die Sozialpolitik der Schweiz"Soziale Praxis und Archiv für Volkswohlfahrt, No. 3, 64-68, 21 January 1926 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 41)
  - "Der Weltbund für Frauenstimmrecht", Soziale Praxis und Archiv für Volkswohlfahrt, No. 26, 645-646, 30 June 1926 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 42)
  - "Die Heimatarbeit nach den Berichten der Gewerbeaufsichtsbeamten. I"Soziale Praxis und Archiv für Volkswohlfahrt, No. 27, 674-678, 8 July 1926 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 43)
  - "Die Frage der Verhütung der Arbeitslosigkeit durch Beeinflussung der Volkswirtschaft"Soziale Praxis und Archiv für Volkswohlfahrt, No. 30, 753-754, 29 July 1926 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 44)
  - "Die Frage des Verhältnisses der unproduktiven zu den produktiven Arbeitskräften"Soziale Praxis und Archiv für Volkswohlfahrt, No. 32, 805-807, 12 August 1926 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 45)
  - "Aus den Berichten der Gewerbeaufsichtsbeamten (Preußen, Bayern, Sachsen, Baden, Württemberg, Braunschweig, Hamburg) für das Jahr 1925"Soziale Praxis und Archiv für Volkswohlfahrt, No. 31, 32, 34, 35, 38, 5 August-23 September 1926 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 46)
  - "Neue Ergebnisse der Ermüdungsforschung"Soziale Praxis und Archiv für Volkswohlfahrt, No. 36, 914-918, 9 September 1926 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 47)
  - "Die wirtschaftliche Lage der Arbeitnehmer in der Schweiz und die sozialpolitische Entwicklung im Jahre 1925"Soziale Praxis und Archiv für Volkswohlfahrt, No. 45, 1140-1144, 11 November 1926 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 48)
  - Soziale Praxis und Archiv für Volkswohlfahrt. Scattered issues, 1923-1926 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 49)
  - "Dienstverhältnisse und Ausbildung der Arbeitsvermittler"Soziale Praxis und Archiv für Volkswohlfahrt, No. 5, 107-111, 3 February 1927 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 50)
  - "The German Accidental Death or (Personal Injury) Insurance"Welfare Work, 29-39, 1927 February (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 51)
  - "Der Entwurf eines Gesetzes zur Abänderung der Arbeitszeitverordnung"Soziale Praxis und Archiv für Volkswohlfahrt, No. 10, 241-242, 10 March 1927 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 52)
  - "Schlußwort zur Diskussion um Cassel"Soziale Praxis und Archiv für Volkswohlfahrt, No. 16, 395-397, 21 April 1927 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 53)
  - "Aus den Berichten der Gewerbeaufsichtsbeamten (Preußen, Bayern, Sachsen, Baden, Württemberg, Braunschweig, Hamburg, Thüringen, Oldenburg) für das Jahr 1926, I -- X", No. 36-45, 8 September-10 November 1927 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 54)
  - "Die endgültige Festsetzung der Grenzen der Landesarbeitsämter"Soziale Praxis und Archiv für Volkswohlfahrt, No. 46, 1156-1158, 17 November 1927 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 55)
  - "Die Arbeit von Kindern, Jugendlichen und Frauen. Aus den Berichten der Gewerbeaufsichtsbeamten für das Jahr 1926"Fortschritte der Gesundheitsfürsorge, No. 6, 1928 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 56)
  - "Evangelische Wirtschaftsethik"Soziale Praxis. Zentralblatt für Sozialpolitik und Wohlfahrtspflege, No. 6, 121-127, 9 February 1928 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 57)
  - "Sozialpolitische Selbstverwaltung. II. Zur Problematik"Soziale Praxis und Archiv für Volkswohlfahrt, No. 41, 969-974, 11 October 1928 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 58)
  - "Worte zur sozialen Arbeit". Excerpt from Der Kampf um die Sozialversicherung, in Soziale Arbeit, Ausgabe A, No. 14, [1], 12 April 1930 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 59)
  - "Der Einfluß der Rationalisierung auf die Arbeitnehmer nach den Berichten der Gewerbeaufsichtsbeamten für das Jahr 1927"Soziale Praxis und Archiv für Volkswohlfahrt, No. 42, 43, 18-25 October 1928 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 60)
  - "Vom Sinn der Wohlfahrtspflege. Gedanken zur Jubiläumstagung des Deutschen Vereins für öffentliche und private Fürsorge"Soziale Praxis und Archiv für Volkswohlfahrt, No. 47, 1104-1106, 20 November 1930 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 61)
  - "Jastrow, Ignaz", ca. 1931-1932 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 62)
  - "Die Kreditkrise"Soziale Praxis. Zentralblatt für Sozialpolitik und Wohlfahrtspflege, No. 31, 1009-1013, 30 July 1931 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 63)
  - "Weltkrise"Soziale Praxis. Zentralblatt für Sozialpolitik und Wohlfahrtspflege, No. 41, 1361-1368, 8 October 1931 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 64)
  - "Die Zweite Internationale Konferenz für Soziale Arbeit. II (Schluß)"Soziale Praxis. Zentralblatt für Sozialpolitik und Wohlfahrtspflege, No. 30, 28 July 1932, 936-945; "Die deutsche Wirtschaft nach Lausanne", 945-951, Undated (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 65)
  - Soziale Praxis. Zentralblatt für Sozialpolitik und Wohlfahrtspflege. Scattered issues, 1933 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 66)
  - "The Tragedy of Unionism in Germany"The Management Circle, 16, 20, 1941 February (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 67)
  - Reviews of writings by Frieda Wunderlich, Undated; 5.40
    - "Der Kampf um die Sozialversicherung", Undated (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 68)
    - "Der Zweck der Wirtschaft", 1924 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 69)
    - Produktivität, 1926 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 70)
    - "Krisenursachen -- Krisenüberwindung", 1931 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 71)
    - Versicherung, Fürsorge und Krisenrisiko, 1932 (Box 1 (5-Published writings of Frieda Wunderlich), Folder 72)